Woohoo!
燃起来了！！
The topic of this final week,
本周结局篇的内容
among our advanced topics, is cache oblivious algorithms.
依然是高级课题——高速缓存参数无关算法
This is a particularly fun area, one dear to my heart
这个算法相当有前途啊 我都快嫁给它了
because I've done a lot of research in this area.
因为我在这个领域已经做了大量的研究
This is an area co-founded by Professor Leiserson. So, in fact
我们的很萌的查教授参与了这个领域的创立
the first context in which I met Professor Leiserson
我与查哥第一次邂逅的缘由
was him giving a talk about cache oblivious algorithms
正是他的一个缓参无关算法的讲座
at WADS '99 in Vancouver I think.
还记得 那是99年的温哥华WADS会议
Am I get that right? Yeah, that has to be an odd year.
我没记错吧？ 嗯 大概是有一年多的事情吧
So, I learned about cache oblivious algorithms then,
正是那时 我了解了缓参无关算法
started working in the area,
开启了我的研究之旅
and it's been a fun place to play.
做研究真的好开心啊
But this topic in some sense was also
而且这个课题 在某种意义上
developed in the context of this class.
是在这门课上发扬光大的
I think there was one semester,
曾经有一个学期
probably also '98-'99 where all of the problem sets
大概是98年到99年 那时课后的习题
were about cache oblivious algorithms.
都是缓参无关算法相关的
And they were, in particular, working out
正是那一年的学生们
the research ideas at the same time.
寓研于学 同时发展起了这个问题的研究思想
So, it must have been fun semester.
史称《那些年我们研究过的算法》
We consider doing that this semester,
这学期 我们本来也想这么搞
but we kept it to the simple.
但现在都浮云了
We know a lot more about cache oblivious algorithms by now
我们现在已经对这个算法相当了解了
as you might expect.
喜闻乐见的事儿了
Right, I think that's all the setting. I mean,
好吧 这就是一些故事的设定
it was kind of developed also with a bunch of MIT students
它是由一群MIT大牛学生开发的
in particular, an M.Eng. student, Harold Prokop.
特别是一个工程硕士 H神
It was his M.Eng. thesis.
这是他的硕士论文
There is all the citations I will give for now.
我就说这么多了
I haven't posted yet, but there are some...
虽然我还没发布 但其实
there are lecture notes that are already on my webpage.
有一些相关的资料在我的主页上
But I will link to them from the course website that gives
我之后会把它们整理到课程主页上去
all the references for all the results I'll be talking about.
把我说的所有相关材料都整理起来
They've all been done in the last five years or so,
那都是5年来的研究成果
in particular, starting in '99
始于1999年
when the first paper was published.
第一篇论文就是那时候发的
But I won't give the specific citations in lecture.
详细的援引我就不在课上说了
And, this topic is related to the topic of last week,
另外 这个课题跟我们上周的课题息息相关
multithreaded algorithms, although at a somewhat high level.
多线程算法 虽然是更高层次上的联系
And it's also dealing with parallelism in modern machines.
这个算法针对的是当今计算机的并行化
And we've had throughout all of these last two lectures,
而在我们上周的两次课里
we've had this very simple model of a computer
我们用的是一个非常简单的计算机模型
where we have random access.
它是随机读写的
You can access memory at a cost of one.
读写内存的花费是O(1)
You can read and write a word of memory.
你可以从内存中读或写一个字段
There is some details on how big a word can be and whatnot.
而一个字段有多大 它有一些详细的定义
It's pretty basic, simple, flat model.
但它是一个基础 简单 单一的模型
And, at the multithreaded algorithm is the idea that, well
而所谓的多线程 也就是说
maybe you have multiple threads of computation running at once
你同时有多个线程的运算在工作
but you still have this very flat memory.
但你同时只有单一的内存
Everyone can access anything in memory at a constant cost.
每个线程读写内存的花费都是常数阶的
We're going to change that model now.
不过这次我们要换一个模型
And we are going to realize that a real machine,
我们要认识到 现实中的机器
the memory of a real machine is some hierarchy.
它的存储模块是分层的
You have some CPU, you have some cache,
首先你有处理器 然后是缓存
probably on the same chip, level 1 cache,
一级缓存可能就在同一个芯片上
you have some level 2 cache,
然后到二级缓存
if you're lucky, maybe you have some level 3 cache,
如果你的机子还没淘汰 那你应该有三级缓存
before you get to main memory.
然后才到内存
And then, you probably have a really big disk
然后 才轮到大硬盘
and probably there's even some cache out here,
硬盘里可能也有一些缓存
but I won't even think about that.
但我这里不作考虑
So, the point is,
重点就是
you have lots of different levels of memory
你有很多层的存储
and what's changing here is that
它们的不同点是
things that are very close to the CPU
越靠近处理器的存储
are very fast to access. Usually level 1 cache
速度就越快 一般来说 一级缓存的话
you can access in one clock cycle or a few.
只需要差不多一个处理器周期
And then, things get slower and slower.
后面的存储就越来越慢
Memory still costs like 70 ns or so
内存大概要70纳秒左右
to access a chunk out of. And that's a long time.
才能获取一定的信息 这个时间已经很长了
70 ns is, of course, a very long time.
70纳秒对于处理器来说 相当漫长
So, as we go out here, we get slower.
我们越往这边走 信息的读写就越慢
But we also get bigger. I mean,
但存储空间就越大
if we could put everything at level 1 cache,
如果所有存储都在一级缓存这儿
the problem would be solved.
问题就解决了
You know that would be a flat memory.
你只知道这有块单一的存储
Accessing everything in here,
如果要读取里面的信息
we assumed takes the same amount of time.
我们假设它的时间都是一样的
But usually, we can't afford, it's not even possible
但通常 我们做不到 也不可能做到
to put everything in level 1 cache. I mean,
把所有东西塞在一级缓存里 我想说
there's a reason why there is a memory hierarchy.
存储的分层结构是有原因的
Does anyone have a suggestion on what that reason might be?
有没有人能给个理由
It's like one of these limits in life. Yeah?
人生总有些极限无法逆袭 请说
Fast memory is expensive.
因为快速存取存储器很贵
That's the practical limitations indeed,
这确实很现实的一个限制
you could try to build more and more at level 1 cache
你可以试着给电脑加上一堆一级缓存
and maybe you could try to, well, yeah.
可能你可以试试看
Expenses is a good reason, and practically,
价钱确实是个好理由 很实际
that's why they may be the sizes are what they are.
这是它们这么袖珍的一个原因
But suppose really fast memory were really cheap.
但假如快速存取存储器很便宜
Really fast memory were really cheap.
而大家又都是高帅富
There is a physical limitation of what's going on, yeah?
是不是还有一个无法超越的物理极限
The speed of light.
光速
Yeah, that's a bit of a problem, right?
爱因斯坦笑了 这问题不好整
No matter how much, let's suppose
假设无论是多是少
you can only fit so many bits in an atom.
一个原子里只能装一定的位信息
You can only fit so many bits in a particular amount of space.
在这个空间里 你只能写这么多位了
If you want more bits, and you need more space,
如果你要更多位 你就要更多的空间
and the more space you have,
而如果空间越大
the longer it's going to take for a round-trip.
光的往返时间就越长
So, if you assume your CPU is like this point in space,
假设你的处理器就是空间中的一个点
so it's relatively small and it has to get the data in,
这个点很小 然后它要从别处获取数据
the bigger the data, the farther it has to be away.
数据越大 离它的平均距离就越远
But, you can have these cores around the CPU that are,
不过你可以把处理器周围的东西——
we don't usually live in 3-D,
其实我们也不怎么三维
and chips were usually in 2-D, but never mind.
因为这些芯片一般是二维的 不过没关系
You can have the sphere that's closer to the CPU
你可以把它做成一个球形 包围着处理器
that's a lot faster to access.
这样获取数据就能很快了
And as you get further away it costs more.
越往外时间花费就越多
And that's essentially what this model is representing,
这就是这个模型要表达的东西
although it's a bit approximated from the
虽然这只是个大致的理论
intrinsic physics and geometry and whatnot.
是从它固有的物理和几何的角度上推导出的
But that's the idea. The latency, the round-trip time
但大概就是这样 延迟和往返时间
to get some of this memory has to be big.
越大的存储就会越慢
In general, the costs to access memory
一般来说 读写内存的花费
is made up of two things, the latency, the round-trip time
就是由延迟和往返时间 这两样组成
which in particular is limited by the speed of light.
这都受到了光速的限制
And, plus the round-trip time,
除了往返时间
you also have to get the data out.
你还要算数据的读取时间
And depending on how much data you want,
这也要看你的数据有多大
it could take longer. OK, so there's something.
数据越大 时间越长 所以说
There could be, get this right, let's say,
这就是 要准确地描述 我们说
the amount of data divided by the bandwidth.
数据量 除以 带宽
OK, the bandwidth is at what rate can you get the data out?
带宽就是你读取数据的频率
And if you look at the bandwidth of these
你会留意到这些不同层次的存储
various levels of memory, it's all pretty much the same.
它们的带宽几乎都是一样的
If you have a well-designed computer
如果你的电脑没什么问题
the bandwidths should all be the same.
它们的带宽就都应该是一致的
OK, as you can still get data off disc really, really fast,
你从硬盘里读数据是很快的
usually at about the speed of your bus,
一般就是你总线的速度
and then the bus gets the CPU hopefully
而总线传入处理器的速度
as fast as everything else.
所有部件是都是一样快的
So, even though they're slower,
所以 虽然它们比较慢
they're really only slower in terms of latency.
但它们的慢都是因为延迟的关系
And so, this part is maybe reasonable.
所以 虽然这一半公式是合理的
The bandwidth looks pretty much the same universally.
但因为大家的带宽都相同
It's the latency that's going up.
所以 时间增大的就是延迟了
So, if the latency is going up but we still
那么 如果延迟在不断增大
get to divide by the same amount of bandwidth,
而每层的除数带宽又相同的话
what should we do to make the access cost
我们要怎么做才能够
at all these levels about the same?
让每一层的时间都大致相等呢？
This is fixed. Let's say this is increasing,
这个是固定的 不不不 这个是递增的
but this is still staying big.
但这个分母却不变
What could we do to balance this formula?
那我们要怎么做才能使公式平衡？
Change the amounts.
改变数据的读取量
As the latency goes up, if we increase the amount,
随着延迟的增大 如果我们增大数据读取量
then the amortized cost to access one element will go down.
那么读取每个元素的平摊花费就减少了
So, this is amortization in a very simple sense.
好的 这个平摊分析很明显了
So, this was to access a whole block,
上面是读取一个数据块的是花费
let's say, and this amount was the size of the block.
这个读取量就是数据块的大小
So, the amortized cost, then, to access one element
那么 读取一个元素的平摊花费
is going to be the latency divided by the size of the block,
就会是 延迟除以数据块大小
the amount plus one over the bandwidth.
再加上带宽的倒数
OK, so this is what you should
好了 这条式子你们都应该
implicitly be thinking in your head.
在脑海中好好思考一下
So, I'm just dividing here by the amounts because
我在这里除掉数据量是因为
the amount is how many elements you get
数据量就是你在一次读取中
in one access, let's suppose.
所获取的元素的数量
OK, so we get this formula for the amortized cost.
好的 我们有了一条平摊花费的公式
The one over bandwidth is going to be good
而后面这一项 带宽的倒数
no matter what level we are on, I claim.
与存储的层次结构无关
There's no real fundamental limitation there
这一项没有什么本质的限制
except it might be expensive.
除了它可能也很大
And the latency we get the amortized out by the amounts,
延迟这一项 则被读取量平摊开来
so whatever the latency is,
所以 无论延迟有多大
as the latency gets bigger out here,
它要是越大
we just get more and more stuff and then
我们只要读取得越多
we make these two terms equal, let's say.
我们就能使得这两项 (之和) 相等
That would be a good way to balance things.
这样就能很好地保持平衡
So in particular, disc has a really high latency.
特别是硬盘 它的延迟一般都很高
Not only is there speed of light issues here,
不仅是因为光速的原因
but there's actually the speed of the head
实际上 主要的问题是磁头速度
moving on the tracks of the disk.
磁头在硬盘磁道上移动
That takes a long time. There's a physical motion.
要花费很多时间 因为这是普通物质运动
Everything else here doesn't usually have physical motion.
而在其他存储层 那都不是普通物质运动
It's just electric.
那是电子的运动
So, this is really, really slow and latency,
所以 硬盘真的很慢很延迟
so when you read something out of disk,
如果你要从硬盘里读取信息
you might as well read a lot of data from disc,
你最好一次就读很多很多
like a megabyte or so. It's probably even old these days.
过去一次读取 1MB 的方式弱爆了
Maybe you read multiple megabytes when you read
你可能要一次读几个MB才行
anything from disk if you want these to be matched.
这样你才能让这两项相均衡
OK, there's a bit of a problem with doing that.
好吧 但这种做法会有个问题
Any suggestions what the problem would be?
谁能谈谈这会有什么问题？
So, you have this algorithm. You know.
好好掂量下这个算法
And, whenever it reads something off of disk,
每当它要从硬盘里读取一个元素
it reads an entire megabyte of stuff
它就要把目标元素附近几MB数据
around the element it asked for.
全部都给读出来
So the amortized cost to access is going to be reasonable,
这样一来 平摊的花费才比较合适
but that's actually sort of assuming something. Yeah?
但实际上 这也有个前提
[Student]:...
[学生]:...
[Prof]:Right. I'm assuming that
[教授]:没错 这个前提就是
I'm ever going to use the rest of that data.
读出来的所有数据我都用得上
If I'm going to read 10 MB around the one
比如 假设我们每次读取10MB数据
element that asked for, I access A bracket I,
虽然实际上 A[i]才是我们真正请求的
and I get 10 million items from A around I,
但我们还是得到了一千万个A[i]周边元素
it would be kind of good if the algorithm
不过要是真的能用得上所有数据
actually used that data for something.
那就真的无敌了
It seems reasonable. So, this would be spatial locality.
但这好像也是可行的 因为数据分布有空间局部性
So, we want, I mean the goal of this world
好了 我们故事的主线目标是
in cache oblivious algorithms and cache efficient algorithms
在这个缓参无关和高效缓存算法的世界中
in general is you want algorithms that
让你的算法能够这种情况下
perform well when this is happening.
有着出色的表现
So, this is the idea of blocking.
这就是数据“块化”的思想
And we want the algorithm to use all or
我们希望在数据块中所有的元素
at least most of the elements in a block,
或者至少大部分的元素 都能派上用场
a consecutive chunk of memory.
这是个连续的数据存储块
So, this is spatial locality.
所以 这样就是空间局部性了
Ideally, we'd use all of them right then. But I mean,
理想情况下 我们能用上所有元素 但我说
depending on your algorithm, that's a little bit tricky.
这也得看你的算法如何 因为这也是有技巧的
There is another issue, though.
但那又是另一回事儿了
So, you read in your thing into,
好吧 如果你要读取数据
read your 10 MB into main memory, let's say,
譬如说读取10MB的数据到内存里
and your memory, let's say, is at least,
而你的内存又至少有...
these days you should have a 4 GB memory or something.
现在你没个4G内存都不好意思说那是电脑了
So, you could read and actually
所以 你能可以往内存里
a lot of different blocks into main memory.
塞入好多好多的数据块
What you'd like is that you can use those blocks
而你的目标则是 这些数据块在内存的保质期
for as long as possible. Maybe you don't even use them.
是越长越好 虽然你不一定会用得上
If you have a linear time algorithm, you're probably
如果你的算法是时间是线性的 那你就有可能
only going to visit each element a constant number of times
只对每个元素访问常数次
So, this is enough.
但这就够了
But if your algorithm is more than linear time,
但如果你的算法时间是高于线性的
you're going to be accessing elements more than once.
那你对数据的访问就不止一次了
So, it would be a good idea
这样一来 高效的算法
not only to use all the elements of the blocks,
就不仅是能用上所有元素那么简单
but use them as many times as you can
而且使用次数还要越多越好
before you have to throw the block out.
把数据彻底压榨干了 再让它回硬盘里
That's temporal locality.
而这就是时间局部性
So ideally, you even reuse blocks as much as possible.
理想情况下 你能不断地重复使用数据块
So, I mean, we have all these caches.
所以说 既然我们有了缓存——
So, I didn't write this word.
啊噢 我忘了把它写下来了
Just in case I don't know how to spell it,
人家才不是因为不会拼单词才没写的
it's not the money.
人家可是拼词小王子呀
We should use those caches for something.
——我们就应该把缓存派上用场
I mean, the fact that they store more than one block,
事实上 缓存能储存不止一个数据块的内容
each cache can store several blocks. How many?
每个缓存都能存好几个块 具体是多少
Well, we'll get to that in a second.
过会儿 答案自然就会揭晓
OK, so this is the general motivation,
好的 这就是我们的主线目标
but at this point the model is still pretty damn ugly.
但到目前为止 这个模型还是有点坑爹
If you wanted to design an algorithm
如果你要设计一个算法
that runs well on this kind of machine directly,
让它在这种机子上直接运行
it's possible but pretty difficult,
不是不行 只是很有难度
and essentially never done, let's say,
说白了 就是实际不可行
even though this is what real machines look like.
即使这就是计算机真实的样子
At least in theory, and pretty much in practice,
在一些理论中和在大部分实践上
the main thing to think about is two levels at a time.
我们主要考虑的是 两层存储结构
So, this is a simplification where we can
这样就能把问题简化
say a lot more about algorithms,
从而集中讨论算法
a simplification over this model.
这是对这一个模型的简化
So, in this model, each of these levels
在这个模型里 每一层存储
has different block sizes, and a different total sizes,
都有不同的数据块大小 不同的存储大小
it's a mess to deal with and design algorithms for.
这简直比七国还乱 还何谈算法设计
If you just think about two levels, it's relatively easy.
但如果你只考虑两层结构 那就容易多了
So, we have our CPU which we assume
所以 假设我们的处理器
has a constant number of registers only.
它只有一定数量的寄存器
So, you know, once it has a couple of data items,
也就是说 只要它存了几个数据
you can add them and whatnot.
你就能做相加等运算
Then we have this really fast pipe.
然后 我们有条非常快的传输线
So, I draw it thick to some cache.
所以我画得很宽 把它连到缓存里
So this is cache. And, we have a relatively narrow pipe
然后这就是缓存 它的传输线就比较窄了
to some really big other storage,
它连向一个灰常大的存储
which I will call main memory.
我把它称为内存
So, I mean, that's the general picture.
好的 这就是我们的概要图
Now, this could represent any two of these levels.
它可以代表这个模型中的任意两层
It could be between L3 cache and main memory.
它可以代表三级缓存和内存
That's maybe, what the naming corresponds to best.
这一对的名字可能是最吻合的了
Or cache could in fact be main memory,
又或者 图里的缓存代表内存
what we consider the RAM of the machine,
也就是通常说的随机存储器
and what's called a memory over there to be the disk.
而图里的内存则对应的是硬盘
It's whatever you care about.
因你考虑的情况而异
And usually, if you have a program,
而通常 当我们有一个程序时
you know, usually we assume everything fits in main memory.
我们通常会假设 程序整个都在内存里
Then you care about the caching behavior.
那么 我们就只关心缓存的表现
So you probably look between these two levels.
所以 你的着眼点应该在这两层存储之间
That's probably what matters the most in your program
因为那可能就是对程序影响最大的部分
because the cost differential here is really big
因为这两层之间的读取花费很大
If your data doesn't even fit it main memory,
如果你的数据不是都在内存里
and you have to go to disk,
你还要读取硬盘数据的话
then you really care about this level
那你就要更关注这一层了
because the cost differential here is huge.
因为这里的读取花费是航母级的
It's like six orders of magnitude, let's say.
大概是量标的6次方这么多
So, in practice you may think of just
但在实践中 你只需要考虑
two memory levels that are the most relevant.
最为相关的那两层模型就好
OK, now I'm going to define some parameters.
好的 现在我要定义一些参数
I'm going to call them cache and main memory
我把它们称为缓存和内存
just for clarity because I like to think of
这样说会更清楚明了一些 因为我觉得
main memory just the way it used to be.
这里的内存 就是一般内存的感觉
And now all we have to worry about is
而我们现在要考虑的就是
this extra thing called cache. It has some bounded size,
这一块额外的叫缓存的东西 它的大小是有限的
and there's a block size. The block size is B.
我们定义 数据块的大小为B
and a number of blocks is M over B.
数据块的数量为M/B
So, the total size of the cache is M.
所以 缓存的大小就为M
OK, main memory is also blocked into blocks of size B.
好 内存也分成一个个大小为B的数据块
And we assume that it has essentially infinite size.
然后我们假设它是无穷大的
We don't care about its size in this picture.
我们并不关心它的大小
It's whatever is big enough to hold the size of
假设它是足够大 足以装得下
your algorithm, or data structure, or whatever.
你的算法程序 数据结构 等等
OK, so that's the general model.
好的 这就是一般的模型
And for strange, historical reasons,
然后因为某些奇怪的历史原因
which I don't want to get into,
黑历史不堪回首啊
these things are called capital M and capital B.
这些代号就用大写M和大写B来表示了
Even though M sounds a lot like memory,
虽然M听起来更像内存
it's really for cache, and don't ask.
但这确实是指缓存 别问我为什么
OK, this is to preserve history.
都是月亮惹的祸
OK, now what do we do with this model?
好的 现在这个模型要怎么搞？
It seems nice, but now what do we measure about it?
它看似挺高端的 但我们要怎么理解它？
What I'm going to assume is that the cache is really fast.
首先 我们要假设缓存的速度非常快
So the CPU can access cache essentially instantaneously.
所以 处理器访问缓存是一瞬间的事
I still have to pay for the computation that the CPU is doing
虽然处理器还是要花时间来做运算
but I'm assuming cache is close enough that I don't care.
但我假设缓存离处理器很近 不必多管
And that main memory is so big that it has to be far away,
而内存因为太大了 所以它的距离很远
and therefore, this pipe is a problem. I mean,
因此 这个传输线就是一个问题
what I should really draw is that pipe is still thick,
实际上 这条传输线也是很宽的
but is really long. So, the latency is high.
不过因为它很长 所以延迟会很高
The bandwidth is still high.
即使带宽也很高
OK, and all transfers here happened in blocks.
好的 这里所有的传输都是以块计算的
So, when you don't have something,
当你需要某个数据时
so the idea is CPU asks for A of I,
处理器就会请求A[i]
ask for something in memory,
请求在存储里的东西
if it's in the cache, it gets it. That's free.
如果它恰好在缓存里 就搞定了 轻松加愉快
Otherwise, it has to grab the entire block
否则 你就要从内存里面
containing that element from main memory,
读取包含请求元素的一整块数据
brings it into cache, maybe kicks somebody out
把它读到缓存里 如果缓存已满的话
if the cache was full,
还要先清理旧的数据块
and then the CPU can use that data and keep going.
然后处理器才能使用这个数据 继续执行
Until it accesses something else that's not in cache,
直到它又访问到不在缓存的数据为止
then it has to grab it from main memory.
那就又得请求内存了
When you kick something out,
当你清理旧数据时
you're actually writing back to memory. That's the model.
你其实是把它写回到内存里 这就是我们的模型
So, we suppose the accesses to cache are free.
我们假设访问缓存是不花费时间的
But we can still think about the running time of the algorithm.
但我们依然要考虑算法的运行时间
I'm not going to change the definition of running time.
我没有对运行时间的定义作任何改动
This would be the computation time,
它还是指运算时间
or the work, if you want to use multithreaded lingo,
或者按多线程里的术语来说 它也叫工作
Computation time.
这里写运算时间好了
OK, so we still have time,
我们还是要考虑运行时间
and T of N will still mean what it did before.
然后T(N)还是原来的意思
This is just an extra level of refinement of understanding
运行时间只是为了让我们更好地理解
of what's going on. Essentially, measuring the parallelism
这个模型是怎么运作的 更主要是为了衡量
that we can exploit out of the memory system,
这个存储系统所能取得的并行度
that when you access something you actually get B items.
因为当你访问某个元素时 实际是访问了B个元素
So, this is the old stuff.
这些都是学过的知识了
Now, what I want to do is count memory transfers.
而现在我要做的 是计算存储的传输量
These are transfers of blocks, so I should say
因为这是用数据块来传输的 所以应该是
block memory transfers between the two levels,
两层存储间的数据块传输量
so, between the cache and main memory.
缓存和内存之间的传输量
So, memory transfers are either reading reads or writes.
那么 存储的传输无非就是读跟写
Maybe I should say that. These are number of block
无非就是这样 这可以写成是
reads and writes from and to the main memory.
向内存读取和写入的块数量
OK, so I'm going to introduce some notation.
好的 接下来我要引入一些符号
This is new notation, so we'll see how it works out.
这些都是新的符号 我们来看看都是些什么
MT of N I want to represent the number of memory transfers
我用MT(N)来表示存储的传输量
instead of just normal time of the problem of size N.
用来代替大小为N的数据的传输时间
Really, this is a function that depends not only on N
这真的是一个函数 而且它还不单取决于N
but also on these parameters, B and M, in our model.
它还取决我们模型中的参数B和M
So, this is what it should be, MT_B,M(N),
所以 MT_B,M(N)才是它的完全体
but that's obviously pretty messy,
但这就要写一大坨了
so I'm going to stick to MT of N.
所以我还是简写成MT(N)算了
But this will always, because mainly I care about
但我所关注的主要还是
the growth in terms of N. well,
函数关于N的增长 额...
I care about the growth in terms of all things,
其实所有参数的增长我都关注
but the only thing I could change is N.
但我这里能改变的只有N
So, most of the time I only think about,
所以 我就主要关注它了
like when we are writing recurrences, only N is changing.
就像做递归一样 只有N是变化的
I can't recurse on the block size.
我不能递归改变块的大小
I can't recurse on the size of cache.
我也不能递归改变缓存大小
Those are given to me. They're fixed.
这些都是给定的 不能改动
OK, so we'll be changing N mainly.
所以 我们主要还是改动N
But B and M always matter here. They're not constants.
但B和M都会有影响 它们不是常数
They're parameters of the model.
它们都是这个模型的参数
OK, easy enough.
简单明了
This is something called the disk access model,
这也被称为硬盘存取模型
if you like DAM models, or the external memory model,
你也可以叫它DAM模型 外部存储模型
or the cache aware model.
或者缓存敏感模型
Maybe I should mention that; this is the cache aware.
可能我应该写出来 这是缓存敏感的
In general, you have some algorithm that
一般来说 如果你的算法
runs on this kind of model, machine model.
是在这种模型上运行的话
That's a cache aware algorithm.
那它就是缓存敏感算法
OK, we're not too interested in cache aware algorithms.
但我们对缓存敏感算法不是很感兴趣
We've seen one, B trees.
我们学过的B树就是一种
B trees are cache aware data structure.
B树是缓存敏感的数据结构
You assume that there is some block size, B, underlying.
你假设 存储底层有些大小为B的数据块
Maybe you didn't see exactly this model.
虽然你可能不清楚整个模型是如何
In particular, it didn't really matter how big the cache was
但重点是 缓存的大小并不重要
because you just wanted to know, when I read B items,
因为你只是想知道 当我向缓存读入B个元素
I can use all of them as much as possible
我就会尽可能多地用上其中的元素
and figure out where I fit among those B items,
并且找到访问元素在这B个元素中的位置
and that gives me log base B of N memory transfers
这样存储传输次数就是以B为底的log N
instead of log N, which would be, if you just
而不是log N（以2为底） 这种结构快多了
threw your favorite balanced binary search tree. So,
抛弃你们心爱的平衡二叉树吧 骚年
log base B of N is definitely better than log base 2 of N.
以B为底肯定完爆以2为底
B trees are a cache aware algorithm.
B树是一种缓存敏感算法
what we would like to do today and next lecture
但我们今天和下堂课要做的
is get cache oblivious algorithms.
却是缓参无关算法
So, there's essentially only one difference
而实际上 我们只有一个不同点
between cache aware algorithms and cache oblivious algorithms.
来区分 缓存敏感算法 和 缓参无关算法
In cache oblivious algorithms,
在缓参无关算法中
the algorithm doesn't know what B and M are.
算法并不知道B和M是多少
So this is a bit of a subtle point, but very cool idea.
这看似很微妙 但却是非常酷炫
You assume that this is the model of the machine,
你假设这就是计算机的模型
and you care about the number of memory transfers
而你关注的又是存储的传输量
between this cache of size M with blocking B,
大小为B的数据块 从大小为M的缓存
and main memory with blocking B.
传输到数据块同样为B的内存里
But you don't actually know what the model is.
不过 你实际上并不清楚这个模型的具体细节
You don't know the other parameters of the model.
你不知道这个模型的参数
It looks like this, but you don't know the width.
你知道它大概如此 但你不知道它到底有多宽
You don't know the height. Why not?
它到底有多高 为什么不呢？
So, the analysis knows what B and M are.
在分析里 B和M是已知的
We are going to write some algorithms
我们接下来要写的算法
which look just like boring old algorithms that
都是我们在课堂上曾经学过的
we've seen throughout the lecture.
无聊无趣的老算法
That's one of the nice things about this model.
但这也是这个模型的优点之一
Every algorithm we have seen is a cache oblivious algorithm,
那就是 我们以前见过的算法都是缓参无关的
all right, because we didn't even know
没错 因为在此之前
the word cache in this class until today.
我们并不知道缓存的存在
So, we already have lots of algorithms to choose from.
所以 我们现在能选择的算法很多
The thing is, some of them will perform well in this model,
值得注意的是 有些算法在这个模型中表现不俗
and some of them won't. So, we would like to
但某些就不行了 所以我们要
design algorithms that just like our old algorithms
设计出和老算法类似的算法
that happened to perform well in this context,
但又能在这种模型下有良好的表现
no matter what B and M are.
而且与B和M无关
So, another way this is the same algorithm
换句话说 我们设计的算法
should work well for all values of B and M
在各种各样的B和M之下都能高效运行
if you have a good cache oblivious algorithm.
这样才算是好的缓参无关算法
OK, there are a few consequences to this assumption.
好的 这种假设会推出几个推论
In a cache aware algorithm, you can explicitly say,
在缓存敏感算法里 你可以确切地说
OK, I'm blocking my memory into chunks of size B.
我把存储分成大小为B的数据块
Here they are. I was going to store these B elements here,
就像这样 我把B个元素存在一起
because you know B, you can do that.
因为你知道B的大小 你才能这样做
You can say, well, OK, now I want to
你还可以说 好吧 我现在想
read these B items into my cache,
把B个元素读入到缓存里来
and then write out these ones over here.
然后覆盖这一部分的内容
You can explicitly maintain your cache.
你可以明确地管理你的缓存
With cache oblivious algorithms,
但在缓参无关算法里
you can't because you don't know what it is.
你就不能这样做了 因为你不知道
So, it's got to be all implicit.
所有东西都是隐式的
And this is pretty much how caches work anyway
实际上 缓存就是这样运作的
except for disk.
硬盘除外
So, it's a pretty reasonable model. In particular,
所以 这是一个非常合理的模型 特别是
when you access an element that's not in cache,
当你要访问一个不在缓存内的元素
you automatically fetch the block containing that element.
你就要自动请求包含这个元素的数据块
And you pay one memory transfer for that
然后你就要经历一轮的存储传输
if it wasn't already there.
因为它不在缓存里
Another bit of a catch here is,
还有一点值得注意的是
what if your cache is full?
你的缓存要是满了怎么办
Then you've got to kick some block out of your cache.
那你就必须把一个数据块写回
And then, so we need some model of which block
这样一来 我们就要有一个模型来管理
gets kicked out because we can't control that.
哪一块要被写回 因为我们控制不了
We have no knowledge of what the blocks are in our algorithm.
在这种算法里 我们不清楚数据块的细节
So what we're going to assume in this model is the ideal thing
所以 我们假设这是一个理想的模型
that when you fetch a new block, if your cache is full,
当你要获取新的数据块时 如果缓存已满
you evict a block that will be used farthest in the future
你就把"最长"不会用到的数据块写回
Sorry, the furthest.
不好意思 是"最久"
Farthest is distance. Furthest is time.
最长是距离 最久是时间
Furthest in the future.
未来最久不会用到的数据
OK, this would be the best possible thing to do.
好的 这是最完美的方案了
It's a little bit hard to do in practice
不过在现实中很难做到
because you don't know the future generally,
因为你不能预知未来
unless you're omniscient.
除非你是玛雅人
So, this is a bit of an idealized model.
所以说 这是一个理想的模型
But it's pretty reasonable in the sense that
但它也有它的合理性
if you've read the reading handout number 20,
如果你读过我发的资料20的话就能理解
this paper by Sleator and Tarjan,
那是S神和T大的论文
they introduce the idea of competitive algorithms.
他们引入了竞争性算法的理念
So, we only talked about a small portion of that paper
那么 我们只涉及过那篇论文的一小部分
that moved to front heuristic for storing a list.
就是列表存储的移前启发式
But, it also proves that there are strategies,
不过 它也证明了存在一些方法——
and maybe you heard this in recitation.
你或许已经在习题课上听过了
Some people covered it; some didn't,
当然 有些人听过了 有些人没听过
that these are called paging strategies.
——那就是分页策略
So, you want to maintain some cache of pages or blocks,
你想要维持一部份数据块或分页在缓存里
and you pay whenever you have to access
而你一旦要访问不在缓存中的数据
a block that's not in your cache.
你就会有一定的花费
The best thing to do is to always kick out the block
那最好的解决方法 就是把在未来里
that will be used farthest in the future
最久不会用到的数据写回
because that way you'll use all the blocks that are in there.
因为剩下的数据块你都会用到
This turns out to be the offline optimal strategy
这种方法其实是一种离线最优策略
if you knew the future.
因为前提是预知未来
But, there are algorithms that are
不过 确实有一些算法
essentially constant competitive against this strategy.
跟这种策略能形成常数竞争关系
I don't want to get into details because
但我不想详细说明了
they're not exactly constant competitive.
因为它们并不是确切的常数竞争关系
But they are sufficiently constant competitive
但也足以构成常数竞争关系了
for the purposes of this lecture that we can assume this,
我们可以根据这堂课的主旨来作这种假设
not have to worry about it. Most of the time,
但你们不用想太多 在大多数情况下
we don't even really use this assumption.
我们都不会用到这种假设
But there it is. That's the cache oblivious model.
但在这里就会用到 这就是缓参无关算法
It makes things cleaner to think about
这样一来思路会更清晰一点
just anything that should be done, will be done.
如果我们认为应该发生的事情就会发生的话
And you can simulate that with least recently used
你可以用最近最少使用算法来大致模拟
or whatever good heuristic that you want to
或者你也可以用其他的启发式
that's competitive against the optimal.
更好地逼近最优策略
OK, that's pretty much the cache oblivious algorithm.
好吧 缓存无关算法的内容有好多好多
Once you have the two level model,
一旦你有了这个两层模型
you just assume you don't know B and M.
你就得假设 你不知道B和M
You have this automatic request in writing, and whatnot.
无论是读取还是写入 你都要这样假设
A little bit more to say, I guess,
我想 我还要再说一点
it may be obvious at this point,
虽然现在已经很直观
but I've been drawing everything as tables.
但我把图都画成表格的形状了
So, it's not really clear what the linear order is.
所以 你可能看不出来这是线性顺序
Linear order is just the reading order.
线性顺序其实就是读取顺序
So, although we don't explicitly say it most of the time,
所以 虽然我们不会一直显式地说明
a typical model is that memory is a linear array.
存储的一般模型是线性数组
Everything that you ever store in your program
你的程序的一切数据
is written in this linear array.
都是存在这种线性数组里的
If you've ever programmed in Assembly or whatever,
要是你写过汇编什么的 你就明白了
that's the model. You have the address space,
存储模型就是这样 你有一个地址空间
and any number between here and here,
这两头之间的地址都用数字来标记
that's where you can actually, this is physical memory.
然后你就可以...这些都是物理存储
This is all you can write to.
都是写入数据的地方
So, it starts at zero and goes out to,
它从0开始 一直延伸到
let's call it infinity over here.
我们把这里设为无限吧
And, if you allocate some array,
如果你分配了一个数组
maybe it occupies some space in the middle. Who knows?
它可能就会在这中间占用了一些空间 谁知道呢？
OK, we usually don't think about that much.
好吧 我们通常不会管这么多
What I care about now is that memory itself
我现在关注的是存储本身
is blocked in this view.
它是分成一块一块的
So, however your stuff is stored in memory,
无论你怎么存储你的数据
it's blocked into clusters of length B.
它都是分成一块块大小为B的数据簇
So, if this is, let me call it one
所以 如果这是...还是写成1吧
and be a little bit nicer. This is B.
写1方便多了 那这就是B了
This is position B plus one.
那这里就是B+1
This is 2B, and 2B plus one, and so on.
这里就是2B 然后2B+1 如此类推
These are the indexes into memory.
这就是存储数组的标号
This is how the blocking happens.
存储就是这么分成数据块的
If you access something here, you get that chunk from U,
如果你要访问这里 你就要读取以这个U为中心
round it down to the previous multiple of B,
往左走 最靠近它的B倍数地址
round it up to the next multiple of B.
一直到下一个B倍数地址
That's what you always get.
你要把这一整块都读出来
OK, so if you think about some array
那么 如果有一组数组
that's maybe allocated here,
它被分配到了这里
OK, you have to keep in mind that
那你心里就要想着
that array may not be perfectly aligned with the blocks.
这个数组跟数据块不是完美对齐的
But more or less it will be so we don't care too much.
但因为它基本都会变成这样 所以不用太操心
But that's a bit of a subtlety there.
虽然这里确实有一些细节的事情
OK, so that's pretty much the model.
好的 关于模型就说这么多了
So every algorithm we've seen, except B trees,
那么 除了B树以外 每一个我们见过的算法
is a cache oblivious algorithm. And our question is, now,
其实都是缓参无关算法 我们的问题是
we know how everything runs in terms of running time.
我们可以通过运行时间来了解算法的性能
Now we want to measure the number of memory transfers,
而现在 我们想计算存储传输量
It's MT of N.
也就是MT(N)
I want to mention one other fact or theorem.
我想提出一个新的事实或定理
I'll put it in brackets
我把它写到方括号里
because I don't want to state it precisely.
因为我不会写得很严谨
But if you have an algorithm that is efficient on two levels,
如果一个算法在两层模型中是高效的
so in other words, what we're looking at,
换句话说 就是我们要研究的东西
if we just think about the two level world
如果它在两层模型中是高效的
and your algorithm is cache oblivious,
而这个算法又是缓参无关算法
then it is efficient on any number of levels
那么 它在任意多层的模型中
in your memory hierarchy, say, L levels.
它总会是高效的 譬如说L层模型
So, I don't want to define what efficient means.
我这里就不详细定义什么是高效了
But the intuition is, if your machine really looks like this
但直观来说 如果你的机子是这种结构
and you have a cache oblivious algorithm,
而你又有一个缓参无关算法
you can apply the cache oblivious analysis for all B and M.
那对于任意的B和M 你都能应用缓参无关分析
So you can analyze the number of memory transfers here,
那么 你就能分析这个存储传输量
here, here, here, and here.
还有这个和这个...
And if you have a good cache oblivious algorithm,
如果你缓存无关算法还不错
the performances at all those levels has to be good.
那么它在每一层就都会取得很好的性能
And therefore, the whole performance is good.
因此 总的性能也会很好
Good here means asymptotically optimal
很好 == 渐近最优
up to constant factors, something like that.
也就是具有常数阶的竞争性
OK, so I don't want to prove that,
我这里就不证明了
and you can read the cache oblivious papers.
你可以读一下我的缓参无关论文
That's a nice fact about cache oblivious algorithms.
里面提到了关于缓参无关算法的有趣的事实
If you have a cache aware algorithm that
如果你有一个缓存敏感算法
tunes to a particular value of B, and a particular value of M,
它被设定了具体的B和M的值
you're not going to have that property.
那你就失去了这些特性了
So, this is one nice feature of cache obliviousness.
所以 这些都是缓参无关的一些美妙的特性
Another nice feature is when you are coding the algorithm,
还有一个很爽的事就是 当你敲代码的时候
you don't have to put in B and M.
你不需要定义B和M
So, that simplifies things a bit.
拯救程序员于水深火热之中
So, let's do some algorithms.
好的 我们来实际谈谈算法吧
Enough about models.
模型已经说完了
OK, we're going to start out with some really simple things
那么 我们先从一些简单的东西开始
just to get warmed up on the analysis side.
做实际分析前先热热身
The most basic thing you can do
在缓参无关的世界里
that's good in a cache oblivious world is scanning.
你能做到的最基本又有用的事情就是扫描了
So, scanning is just visiting the items in an array in order.
扫描的意思就是把数组的元素按顺序访问一遍
So, visit A_1 up to A_N in order.
从A_1按顺序访问到A_N
For some notion of visit, this is presumably
而对于访问元素来说 大致上
some constant time operation. For example,
花费的时间是常数阶的 比如说
suppose you want to compute the aggregate of the array.
假设你要计算数组元素的总和
You want to sum all the elements in the array.
你要把每一个数组元素加起来
So, you have one extra variable using,
那你就用一个额外的变量来存结果
but you can store that in a register or whatever,
它可以存放在寄存器里面
so that's one simple example. Sum the array.
这就是一个简单的例子 数组求和
OK, so here's the picture. We have our memory.
好的 我画一幅图 这就是我们的内存
Each of these cells represents one item, one element,
每一个单元都表示一个元素
log N bits, one word, whatever.
log N个位 或者一个字 等等
Our array is somewhere in here. Maybe it's there.
我们的数组在这里 也可能是那里
And we go from here to here to here to here.
我们要访问这里 这里 和这里
OK, and so on. So, what does this cost?
如此类推  那花费是多少
What is the number of memory transfers?
存储传输量是多少
We know that this is a linear time algorithm.
我们知道这是一个线性时间算法
It takes order N time.
它花费N阶的时间
What does it cost in terms of memory transfers?
那它花费多少存储传输量呢
N over B, pretty much.
N/B 就是这么多
We like to say it's order N over B
准确来说 是N/B阶的
plus two or one in the big O. This is a bit of worry.
再加上2或者1 大O记号 有点不对喔
I mean, N could be smaller than B.
因为N可能比B还要小
We really want to think about all the cases, especially
我们需要考虑到所有的情况
because usually you're not doing this on something of size N.
特别是因为 你通常也不是用N来计算
You're doing it on something of size k,
你一般用的是k
where we don't really know much about k.
而k则是一个我们不确定的数
But in general, it's N over B plus one
但一般而言 它就是O(N/B+1)
because we always need at least one memory transfer
因为我们至少要传输一个数据块
to look at something, unless N is zero.
才能够做访问操作 除非N是0
And in particular,
值得注意的是
it's plus two if you care about the constants.
如果常数也要考虑 那这就是+2了
If I don't write the big O then it would be plus two at most
如果我不把它写进大O记号里 那它就是+2
because you could essentially waste the first block
因为第一块基本就浪费掉了
and that everything is fine for awhile.
而后面的数据块就会是对齐的
And then, if you're unlucky,
但如果你很不走运的话
you essentially waste the last blocked.
那最后一个数据块也会浪费掉
There is just one element in that block,
一个数据块只有一个可用元素
and you're not getting much out of it.
剩余的空间就浪费了
Everything in the middle, though,
但数组中间的部分
every block between the first and last block has to be full.
中间的这些数据块就都是对齐的
So, you're using all of those elements.
这些元素你都会用上
So out of the N elements, you only have N over B blocks
所以 对于N个元素的数组 你只有N/B个数据块
because the block has B elements.
因为一块里面有B个元素
OK, that's pretty trivial.
这都是些琐碎事情
Let me do something slightly more interesting,
我们来看看一些有趣点的事吧
which is two scans at once.
那就是一次做两个扫描
OK, here we are not assuming anything about M.
好的 在此我们对M不做任何要求
we're not assuming anything about the size of the cache,
我们不对缓存大小做任何要求
just that I can hold a single block.
只要能装下一个数据块就好
The last block that we visited has to be there.
我们最后访问到的数据块必须在缓存里
OK, you can also do a constant number of parallel scans.
好的 其实你可以做任意常数的并行扫描
This is not really parallel
在多线程思想看来
in the sense of multithreaded, bit simulated parallelism.
这并不是严格的并行化 而是模拟并行化
I mean, if you have a constant number,
如果做常数次扫描
do one, do the other, do the other,
那就做第一次 跳去做另一次
come back, come back, come back, all right,
回来做第一次 再跳去做另一次
visit them in turn round robin, whatever.
来回同时地做几次扫描
For example, here's a cute piece of code.
比如说 这有段挺好玩的代码
If you want to reverse an array,
如果你要翻转一个数组
OK, then you can do it. This is a good puzzle.
好的 我们来试下手 这是个好问题
You can do it by essentially two scans
你用两次扫描就能把它做出来
where you repeatedly swapped the first and last element.
只要不断交换第一个和最后一个元素就好
So I was swapping A_i with N minus i plus one,
那我就交换A_i和A_N-i+1
and just restart at one. So, here's your array.
然后从一开始循环 那么 这就是目标数组
Suppose this is actually my array.
假设这真的是我们的数组
I swap these two guys, and I swap these two guys, and so on.
我交换这两个元素 我再交换两个元素 如此类推
That will reverse my array, and this should
然后就得到翻转的数组了
work hopefully the middle as well if it's odd.
如果元素个数是奇数 那到了中间
It should not do anything.
它就不做任何事
And you can view this as two scans.
你可以把这看成是两次扫描
There is one scan that's coming in this way.
一次是从这边扫
There's also a reverse scan, ooh,
一次是反过来扫
some more sophisticated, coming back this way.
好像挺复杂 从这边扫过去
Of course, reverse scan has the same analysis.
当然 反着扫的性能分析是一样的
And as long as your cache is big enough
只要你的缓存足够大
to store at least two blocks,
装得下两个数据块就行
which is a pretty reasonable assumption,
这个假设不过分吧？
so let's write it.
那我们就写下来
Assuming the number of blocks in the cache,
假设缓存中的数据块数量
which is M over B, is at least two in this algorithm,
也就是M/B 在这个算法中 至少是两个
the number of memory transfers is still
那存储的传输量就依然
order N over B plus one.
还是O(N/B+1)阶
OK, the constant goes up maybe,
好吧 常数项可能会增大
but in this case it probably doesn't. But who cares.
但它也有可能不增大 管他呢
OK, as long as you're doing a constant number of scans,
只要你是在做常数个的数组里
in some constant number of arrays,
做常数次的扫描
it happens to be one of them's reversed, whatever,
可能有些扫描是另一个的翻转
it will take, we call this linear time.
它都要 线性的时间花费
It's linear in the number of blocks in your input.
它跟你要读入的数据块成线性关系
OK, great. So now you can reverse an array: exciting.
正啊！ 现在你学会翻转数组了 涨姿势了！
Let's try another simple algorithm on another board.
我们再来试试另外一种简单的算法
Let's try binary search. So just like last week,
我们试试二分搜索 就像上星期
we're going back to our basics here.
我们回到我们的基础
Scanning we didn't even talk about in this class.
扫描算法其实还没讲过呢
Binary search is something we talked about a little bit.
二分搜索倒是讲过一点点
It was a simple divide and conquer algorithm.
这是一个简单的分治法算法
I hope you all remember it. And if we look at an array,
希望你们都能记牢 当我们观察一个数组时
and I'm not going to draw the cells here
我这里就不把单元格都画出来了
because I want to imagine a really big array,
因为我想把它想象成一个超大型数组
binary search, but suppose it always goes to left.
开始二分搜索 假设目标在左边
It starts by visiting this element in the middle.
我们先访问中间的元素
Then it goes to the quarter marked.
然后它跳到1/4点
Then it goes to the one eighth mark.
然后再跳到1/8点
OK, this is one hypothetical execution of a binary search.
好的 这就是我们假想的二分搜索
OK, and eventually it finds the element it's looking for.
最终 我们找到了我们要找的元素
It finds where it fits at least.
它就在不偏不倚的地方
So x is over here. So, we know that it takes log N time.
所以x就在这里 我们知道这要花费log N的时间
How many memory transfers does it take?
那这里有多少存储传输量
Now, I blocked this array into chunks of size B,
现在 我把这个数组分成大小为B的小块
blocks of size B. How many blocks do I touch?
大小为B 那我一共要访问多少块
This one's a little bit more subtle.
好像越来越微妙了
It depends on the relative sizes of N and B, yeah.
这取决于N和B的相对大小 耶啊
Log base B of N would be a good guess.
以B为底的log N是一个不错的选择
We would like it to be, let's say,
我们希望它会是
hope, is that it's log base B of N because we know that
希望它是log_B(N)  因为我们知道
B trees can search in what's essentially
B树的搜索就是这样
a sorted list of N items in log base B of N time.
它本质上就是用log_B(N)的时间 搜索一个顺序表
That turns out to be optimal in the cache oblivious model
这其实就是缓参无关模型里的最优解
or in the two level model
或者说两层模型里的
you've got to pay log base B of N.
你必须花费log_B(N)时间
I won't prove that here.
我就不证明了
The same reason you need log N comparisons
这跟普通的二分搜索
to do a binary search in the normal model.
需要做log N步比较是一样道理
Alas, it is possible to get log base B of N
可惜啊 就算不知道B是多少
even without knowing B. But, binary search does not do it.
取得log_B(N)也是可能的 只是二分搜索做不到
Log of N over B, yes.
正确答案是log N/B
So the number of memory transfers on N items
所以 N个元素的存储传输量
is log of N over B also known as, let's say, plus one,
就是log N/B 又可以看做是——漏了个+1
also known as log N minus log B.
也可以看做是log N - log B
OK, whereas log base B of N is log N divided by log B,
而log_B(N)则可以看成log N / log B
OK, clearly this is much better than subtracting.
很显然 除法要比减法强多了
So, this would be good, but this is bad.
所以 这个是牛叉 这个是渣渣
Most of the time, this is log N,
大部分情况下 这里就是log N
which is no better, I mean, you're not
这跟没有划分数据块的情况一样
using blocks at all essentially.
并没有什么改善
The idea is, out here, I mean,
正确的思路是 这个地方
there's some little tiny block that contains this thing.
有个很小的数据块包含了这个二分点
I mean, tiny depends on how big B is.
当然“很小”也要取决于B的大小
But, each of these items will be in a different block
但这些二分点一般都会在不同的数据块之中
Until you get essentially one block worth of x.
直到你的数据块包含了x为止
When you get within one block worth of x,
当你搜索到包含x的数据块时
there's only like a constant number of blocks that matters,
你可能再搜索几步就到达x了
and so all of these accesses are indeed within the same block.
而这时 这个数据块就包含了接下来所有的二分点
But, how many are there? Well, just log B
有多少个这样的二分点 就是log B个
because you're only spending log B with any
因为你只需要通过log B步搜索
if you're within an interval of size k,
就像 当你在一个大小为k的区间里
you're only going to spend log k steps in it.
你就只要做log k步搜索
So, you're saving log B in here,
所以 这里你就可以省掉log B了
but overall you're paying log N,
但全局来讲 你的花费是log N
so you only get log N minus log B plus some constant.
所以 你就得到了log N - log B加上一个常数
OK, so this is bad news for binary search.
所以 这对于二分搜索是个坏消息
So, not all of the algorithms we've seen
不是所有的算法
are going to work well in this model.
都适合这种模型
We need a lot more thinking before we can solve
我们在解决二分搜索的问题前
what is essentially the binary search problem,
还要先考虑很多的东西
finding an element in a sorted list,
在不知道B的情况下 要如何
in log base B of N without knowing B.
用log_B(N)的时间搜索顺序表
OK, we know we could use B trees.
好吧 我们可以用B树
If you knew B, great, that works, and that's optimal.
如果你知道B的话 正！搞定了 而且是最优解
But without knowing B, it's a little bit harder.
但我们不知道B 这就有难度了
And this gets us into the world of divide and conquer.
然后 我们就看到分治法的圣光在召唤了
Also like last week,
就像上周一样
and like the first few weeks of this class,
同时也像最开始那几周一样
divide and conquer is your friend.
分治法与你同在！
And, it turns out divide and conquer is not the only tool,
其实 分治法不是唯一的方法
but it's a really useful tool in designing
但对于设计缓参无关算法来说
cache oblivious algorithms. And, let me say why.
它确实好使好用 我来解释下为什么
So we'll see a bunch of divide and conquer based algorithms
那么 我们将会看到很多分治法算法
cache oblivious.
都是缓参无关的
And, the intuition is that
直观来看
we can take all the favorite algorithms we have,
我们可以我们喜爱的算法都拿来谈谈
obviously it doesn't always work.
虽然这肯定不是都起作用
Binary search was a divide and conquer algorithm.
二分法就是一个分治法算法
It's not so great. But, in general,
它的表现并不太好 但一般来说
the idea is that your algorithm can just do
我们要的就是 算法能够做出
the normal divide and conquer thing, right?
分治法所做的事 对吧
You divide your problem into subproblems
你把你的问题分成子问题
of smaller size repeatedly,
把问题越分不断细化
all the way down to problems of constant size,
直到问题分成了常数的大小
OK, just like before. But, if you're recursively
好的 跟以前一样 但如果你不断递归
dividing your problem into smaller things,
把大问题分成小问题
at some point you can think about it and say,
到一定程度时 你可能就会想到
well, wait, I mean, the algorithm divides all the way,
等一等 算法还在不断地细分
but we can think about the point at which
但我们可以想 到了某个地步
the problem fits in a block or fits in cache.
问题刚好吻合数据块的大小或者缓存的大小
OK, and that's the analysis.
好的 这就是分析节奏了
We'll think about the time when your problem is small enough
我们要考虑 当问题被充分细分
that we can analyze it in some other way.
我们就能用另外的方法来分析了
So usually, we analyze it recursively. We get a recurrence
通常我们都用递归分析 建立一个迭代过程
What we're changing, essentially, is the base case.
要改变的 基本上就只有考虑最小子问题的单位情况
So, in the base case,
那么 在单位情况中
we don't want to go down to a constant size.
我们不想细分到常数大小
That's too far. I'll show you some examples.
因为那样已经太过了 我举些例子
We want to consider the point in recursion
我想考虑的是在递归过程中
at which either the problem fits in cache,
问题大小刚好与缓存大小吻合的一刻
so it has size less than or equal to M,
所以 问题大小小于或等于M
or it fits in order one blocks.
又或者刚好是一个数据块大小
That's another natural time to do it.
这又是一个恰当的时机
Order one blocks would be even better than fitting in cache.
跟块大小吻合其实比跟缓存吻合还要好
So, this means a size order B.
所以 这就是B阶的大小
OK, this will change the base case of the recurrence,
好的 这就要改变迭代的单位情况了
and it will turn out to give us good answers
而且 结果其实蛮不错
instead of bad ones. So, let's do a simple example.
一点都不赖 我们来做个简单的例子吧
Our good friend order statistics,
接下来要登场的是——顺序统计量
in particular, for finding medians.
它是求中位数时 你最好的朋友
So, I hope you all know this by heart.
所以 我希望你们都能狠狠地记住它
Remember the worst case linear time,
下面是最坏情况线性时间
median finding algorithm by Blum et al.
布霖教授等人的求中位数算法
I'll write this fast. We partition our array.
我会写的很快 我们先给数组分段
It turns out, this is a good algorithm as it is.
这真的是一个感人至深的好算法
We partition our array conceptually into N over five,
我们有意地把数组分为N/5段
five tuples into little groups of five.
每一段里面有5个元素
This may not have been exactly how I wrote it last time.
这可能跟我以前写的有所不同
I didn't check. But, it's the same algorithm.
但我不纠结了 毕竟算法是一样的
You compute the median of each five tuple.
然后 求出每5个元素的中位数
Then you recursively compute
然后 你再递归计算出
the median of the medians of these medians.
这些中位数之中的中位数X
Then, you partition around x.
然后 用中位数X把数组分为两段
So, that gave us some element that was roughly in the middle.
然后 就会得到一些大致在中间的数
It was within the middle half, I think.
至少是在中间的那一片
Partition around x, and then we show that
再用X来将数组对半分 然后我们表示
you could always recurse on just one of the sides.
我们总能在某一半上 递归求出中位数
OK, this was our good old friend for computing,
好的 这个算法是我们的好朋友
order statistics, or medians, or whatnot.
无论是求顺序统计量 还是中位数神马的
OK, so how much time does this, well,
那这要用多少时间呢 啊
we know how much time this takes.
我们已经知道答案了
It should be linear time.
就是线性的时间
But how many memory transfers does this take?
但它又要用多少存储传输量呢
Well, conceptually partitioning that, I can do, in zero.
在这里 有意划分也就是说 我可以不划分
Maybe I have to compute N over five, no big deal here.
可能我有必要划分成N/5段 但这不重要
We're not thinking about computation.
我们又不是在考虑计算量
I have to find the median of each tuple.
我想找出每一小段的中位数
So, here it matters how my array is laid out.
所以 数组元素的分布就会有影响
But, what I'm going to do is take my array,
但是 我要做的是选择我的数组
take the first five elements,
选择前5个元素
and then the next five elements and so on.
接着 再选择5个元素 如此类推
Those will be my five tuples.
每个小段有5个元素
So, I can implement this just by scanning,
所以 我可以直接用扫描
and then computing the median on those five elements,
求出这5个元素的中位数
which I stored in the five registers on my CPU.
它们可以直接存在CPU的寄存器里
I'll assume that there are enough registers for that.
我假设寄存器是足够的
And, I compute the median,
然后 我求出中位数
write it out to some array out here.
把它写在一个数组里
So, it's going to be one element.
然后这就有了一个元素
So, the median of here goes into there.
这小段的中位数写在这儿
The median of these guys goes into there, and so on.
这小段的中位数写在这儿 如此类推
So, I'm scanning in here,
我一边扫描这个数组
and in parallel, I'm scanning an output in here.
一边并发地扫描这个输出数组
So, it's two parallel scans.
两个并行扫描
So, that takes linear time.
都是线性的时间
So, this takes order N over B plus one memory transfers.
所以 这就需要N/B+1的传输量
Then we have recursively compute the median of the medians.
然后我们递归地求出中位数的中位数
This step used to be T of N over five.
这一步的花费本来是T(N/5）
Now it's MT of N over five,
现在则是MT(N/5)
OK, with the same values of B and M.
用的是一样的参数B和M
Then we partition around x.
然后用X来将数组分成两半
Partitioning is also like three parallel scans
分段跟三重并行扫描相似
if you work it out.
你试试就知道了
So, this is also going to take linear memory transfers,
所以 这也要用线性的存储传输量
N over B plus one.
是N/B+1
And then, we recurse on one of the sides,
接着 我们对数组某一边进行递归
and this is the fun part of the analysis
这是当时分析中最有趣的部分
which I won't repeat here.
我就不再安可了
But, we get MT of, like, three quarters N.
但我们得到的是MT(3N/4)
I think originally it was seven tenths,
原本应该是7/10的
so we simplified to three quarters,
不过我们化简成3/4了
which is hopefully bigger than seven tenths.
这应该是比7/10要大
Yeah, it is. OK, so this is the new analysis.
应该没错 好的 这就是新的分析
Now we get a recurrence.
现在 我们得到了一条递归式
So, let's do that.
那就来解这条式吧
So, the analysis is we get this MT of N is MT of N over five
根据分析 我们有MT(N)等于MT(N/5)
plus MT of three quarters N plus, this is just as before.
加上MT(3N/4) 这都跟以前一样
Before we had linear work here.
以前 这里是线性的工作量
And now, we have what we call
而现在 它就变成了
linear number of memory transfers, linear number of blocks.
线性的存储传输量 线性数量的数据块
I'll sort of ignore this plus one. It's not too critical.
我大概会省略掉这个+1 因为它不是很重要
So, this is our recurrence.
好了 这就是我们的递归式
Now, it depends what our base case is.
现在就看单位情况怎么定义了
And, usually we would use a base case of constant size.
通常 单位情况都会定义成常数大小
So, let's see what happens
那我们就来看看
if we use a base case of constant size so that just
单位情况是常数大小会如何
it's clear why this base case is so important.
我们要弄清楚 为什么这个单位情况很重要
This describes a recurrence as one of these hairy recurrences.
这种式子就是我们所说的毛烦递归
And, I don't want to use substitution.
我不会真的用替换法解出来
I just want the intuition of why
我只是想直观地说明
this is going to solve to something rather big.
这条式解出来是一个很大的东西
And for me the best intuition always comes from recursion trees
对我而言 最好的直观的做法就是递归树
If you don't know the solution to recurrence
如果你事先不知道递归式的解
and you need a good guess, use recursion trees.
而你又需要一个好的猜想 那就用递归树吧
And today, I will only give you good guesses.
因为今天 我只想给出一个好的猜想
I don't want to prove anything with substitution
我不想用替换法来做证明
because I want to get to the bigger ideas.
因为我的目标是讨论更大的课题
So, this is even messy from a recursion tree point of view
其实从递归树的角度来看 这可能还会更麻烦
because you have these unbalanced sizes
因为你会得到的树是不平衡的
where you start at the root with some of size N over B.
一开始 你的根的大小为N/B
Then you split it into something size one fifth N over B,
然后它岔开成一个N/5B的分支
and something of size three quarters N over B,
和一个3N/4B的分支
which is annoying because now this subtree
这有点麻烦 因为这边的子树
will be a lot bigger than this one,
会比这一边的要大
or this one will terminate faster.
这边会结束的更快
So, it's pretty unbalanced. But we can...
所以 这会变得很不平衡 但我们可以
summing per level doesn't really tell you a lot at this point.
对每一层都求和好像也帮不了你
But let's just look at the bottom level.
但我们来看看最底层
Look at all the leaves in this recursion tree.
看看这棵树的叶节点
So, that's the base cases.
那它们就是单位情况了
How many base cases are there?
那会有多少个单位情况呢
This is an interesting question.
这个问题很有趣
We've never thought about it in the context of this recurrence.
因为这是条递归式 所以我们从没想过
It gives a somewhat surprising answer.
它会给出一个很意外的结果
It was surprising to me the first time I worked it out.
当我第一次算出来时 我就觉得很意外
So, how many leaves does this recursion tree have?
那么 这棵递归树会有多少个叶节点
Well, we can write a recurrence.
额 我们可以再写一条递归式
The number of leaves in a problem of size N,
这个大小为N的问题里 叶节点的数量
it's going to be the number of leaves in this problem
等于这个子问题的叶节点数
plus the number of leaves in this problem plus zero.
加上这个子问题的叶节点数 再加0
So, that's another recurrence.
好的 我们又得到一条递归式
We'll call this L of N.
我们可以叫它L(N)
OK, now the base case is really relevant.
现在 这个单位情况就很重要了
It determines the solution to this recurrence.
它决定了这个主问题的解
And let's, again, assume that in a problem of size one,
那让我们再次假设问题大小为1的情况
we have one leaf. That's our only base case.
我们有一个叶节点 这就是我们的单位情况
Well, it turns out, and here you need to guess, I think.
我觉得呢 其实我们这里应该要猜想一下
This is not particularly obvious.
因为这并不明显
Any of the TA's have guesses of the form of this solution?
有没有助教能猜到 这个解的形式是怎么样的
Or anybody, not just TA's.
谁都行 不仅是助教
But this is open to everyone.
这就像比智招亲啊
If Charles were here, I would ask him.
如果查哥在的话 我肯定会问他
I had to think for a while, and it's not linear, right,
我们来考虑一下 这应该不是线性的对吧
because you're somehow decreasing quite a bit.
因为它每一步都递减不少
So, it's smaller than linear,
它应该比线性还要小
but it's more than a constant.
但又比常数要大
OK, it's actually more than polylog,
实际上 它也比log多项式要大
so what's your favorite function in the middle?
那么 你们还能想到什么更中间的函数？
N over log N, that's still too big.
N/logN 还是太大了
Keep going. You have an oracle here, so you can,
继续想 爆种吧 骚年
N to the k, yeah, close.
N^k 嗯嗯 很接近了
I mean, k is usually an integer.
我是说 k通常是个整数
N to the alpha for some real number between zero and one.
不如说是N^α  0到1之间的实数
Yeah, that's what you meant.
你说的是这个吧
Sorry. It's like the shortest mathematical joke.
抱歉 这就像是最短数学的冷笑话
Let epsilon be less than zero or
令ε小于0 又或者
for a sufficiently large epsilon. I don't know.
令ε充分大 好冷
So, you've got to use the right letters.
所以说 符号很重要
So, let's suppose that it's N to the alpha.
那我们假设它是N^α
Then we would get this N over five to the alpha,
所以我们得到 这是(N/5)^α
and we'd get three quarters N to the alpha.
这个是(3N/4)^α
When you have a nice recurrence like this,
当你的递归式是这么有美感的话
you can just try plugging in a guess and see whether it works,
你就可以直接猜一个结果代入 看看可不可行
OK, and of course this will work only depending on alpha.
这当然是对的咯 只要α找对
So, we should get an equation on alpha here.
那么 我们会得到一个关于α的方程
So, everything has an N to the alpha,
所有东西都是N^α
in fact, all of these terms.
没错 每一项都是
So, I can divide through my N to the alpha.
那么 我可以两边都除以N^α
That's assuming that it's not zero or something.
这相当于假设它不为0
That seems reasonable.
挺合理的嘛
So, we have one equals one fifth to the alpha
那么 我们有1等于(1/5)^α
plus three quarters to the alpha.
加上(3/4)^α
This is something you won't get on a final
放心 这个期末不会考
because I don't know any good way to solve this
因为我都不知道有什么好的解法
except with like Maple or Mathematica.
这时用Maple或Mathematica就好了
If you're smart I'm sure you could compute it in a nicer way,
要是你很有才的话 你一样能很好地解出来
but alpha is about 0.8, it turns out.
而结果大致是α=0.8
So, the number of leaves is this
所以 叶节点的数量
sort of in between constant and linear.
介乎于常数和线性之间
Usually polynomial means you have an integer power.
虽然一般多项式都是指整数幂
Let's call it a polynomial. Why not?
我们姑且叫它多项式吧
There's a lot of leaves, is the point,
重点是这有很多的叶节点
and if we say that each leaf costs
如果每一个都要花费
a constant number of memory transfers, we're in trouble
常数阶的存储传输量 我们就有麻烦了
because then the number of memory transfers
因为如果这样 存储的传输量
has to be at least this. If it's at least that,
至少都有这么多 如果这是至少的话
that's potentially bigger than N over B,
它就很有可能超越N/B
I mean, bigger than in an asymptotic sense.
如果用渐进分析来看的话
This is little omega of N over B if B is big.
这个就是ω(N/B) 如果B足够大...
If B is at least N to the 0.2 something,
如果B至少有N^0.2这么大
OK, or one seventh something.
或者是N^(1/7)这么大
But if, in particular, B is at least N to the 0.2,
如果B恰恰至少是N^0.2这么大
then this should be bigger than that.
那么这个就会比它要大了
So, this is a bad analysis because we're
所以根据分析 这也不给力
not going to get the answer we want, which is N over B.
因为它是不我们想要的 不是N/B
The best you can do for median is N over B
求中位数最好的性能是N/B
because you have to read all the element,
因为你必须读取所有的元素
and you should spend linear time.
你必须花费线性的时间
So, we want to get N over B.
所以 我们要的是N/B
This algorithm is N over B plus one.
这个算法是N/B+1
So, this is why you need a good base case, all right?
所以 这就是为什么单位情况那么重要的原因了
So that makes the point.
这就说到点上了
So, the question is, what base case should I use?
那么问题就来了 我要用什么样的单位情况呢
So, we have this recurrence
现在 我们有这条递归式
What base case should I use? Constant was too small.
我应该给它什么样的单位条件 常数就太小了
We have a couple of choices listed up here.
上面这里列出了好几种选择
Any suggestions?
元芳 你怎么看
B, OK, MT of B is?
B 好的 MT(B)是多少
Ah. The hard part.
啊哈 被难住了吧
So, if my problem, if the size of my array
如果我的问题 或是我的数组大小
fits in a block and I do all this stuff on it,
跟数据块大小吻合 数据都能放在一个块里
how many memory transfers could that take?
那一共要多少存储传输量
One, or a constant, depending on alignment.
1 或者是常数个 要看对齐的情况如何
OK, maybe it takes two memory transfers, but constant.
或者只需要两个传输量 但还是常数阶
Good. That's clearly a lot better than this base case,
不错 这明显比这个单位条件好
MT of one equals order one, clearly stronger.
这是MT(1)=O(1) 完爆啊
So, hopefully, it gives the right answer,
所以 这应该是正解没跑了
and now indeed it does.
确实如此
I love this analysis. So, I'm going to wave my hands.
我非常喜欢这个分析 喜欢到手舞足蹈
OK, but in particular, what this gives us,
好的 但这又说明了什么
if we do the previous analysis,
回想下前面的分析
what is the number of leaves?
叶节点的数量会是多少呢
So, in the leaves, now L of B equals one
好 在叶节点的分析里 现在L(B)=1
instead of L of one equals one.
不再是L(1)=1
So, this stops earlier. When does it stop?
所以 递归提早终止了 具体是什么时候
Well, instead of getting N to the order of 0.8, whatever,
现在不是N^0.8神马的了
we get N over B to the power of 0.8 whatever.
现在是(N/B)^0.8神马的了
So it turns out the number of leaves is N over B to the alpha,
所以现在变成 叶节点数为(N/B)^α
which is little o of N over B.
也就是o(N/B)
So, we don't care. It's tiny.
这个很小 所以不重要了
And, if you look at the root cost
你再看看根节点
is N over B in the recursion tree,
它的花费是N/B
the leaf cost is little o of N over B,
而叶节点数则是o(N/B)
and if you wave your hands, and close your eyes, and squint,
然后 你头发甩甩 挥手摆摆 你就能知道
the cost should be geometrically decreasing as we go down,
花费是顺着树往下几何递减的
I hope, more or less.
我觉得差不多是这样了
It's a bit messy because of all the things terminating,
可能有一点乱 因为节点终结速度不一样
but let's say cost is roughly geometric.
不过 它大致上是几何递减的
We don't do this in the final,
期末考试就不要这要写了
but you won't have any messy recurrences like this.
不过你也不会碰到这种毛烦递归的
So, don't worry.
放心吧
Down the tree, so you'd have to prove this formally,
沿着树往下 额 这个你是要证明的
but I claim that the root cost dominates.
我这里只断言 根节点的花费占支配地位
And, the root cost is N over B.
然后 根节点花费为N/B
So, we get N over B. OK, so this is a nice,
所以 我们得到N/B 好 这是一个
linear time algorithm for order statistics
很不错的线性顺序统计量算法
for cache oblivious. Great.
对于缓参无关算法来说 强大
This may turn you off a little bit,
虽然你们会有点蛋疼
but even though this is like the simplest algorithm,
但即使像这样的最最简单算法
it's also probably the most complicated analysis that we will do
一样可能会有最最复杂的分析
In the future, our algorithms will be more complicated,
以后 我们的算法会越来越复杂
and the analyses will be relatively simple.
分析却反而相对地简单
And usually, it's that way with cache oblivious algorithms.
一般来说 缓参无关算法就是这种性质
So, I'm giving you this sort of as
为什么这样就够了呢
the intuition of why this should be enough.
我大致给了你们一些直观的解释
Then you have to prove it.
而你们则要去自己证明
OK, let's go to another problem
好的 我们来看下一个算法
where divide and conquer is useful,
这次分治法就很有用了
our good friend, matrix multiplication.
又来一个老朋友——矩阵乘法
I don't know how many times we've seen this in this class,
我都不知道在这门课上讲过多少次了
but in particular we saw it last week
其实上周我们才讲过
with a recursive matrix multiply, multithreaded algorithm.
那时是讲多线程算法 递归的矩阵相乘
So, I won't give you the algorithm yet again,
所以 我就不再具体说算法了
but we're going to analyze it in a very different way.
但我们会用另一种方法来分析它
So, we have C and we have A and...
好的 我们有C 我们有A...
actually, up to you.
还是看你们怎么选吧
So, I could cover standard matrix multiplication,
我可以将基本的矩阵乘法
which is when you do it row by row, and column by column.
也就是一行一行 一列一列这样相乘
And, we could see why that's bad. And then,
我们可以看看为什么是这样不好 然后
we could do the recursive one and see why that's good.
我们再做递归乘法 看看为什么这样会比较好
Or, we could skip the standard algorithm.
或者 我们直接跳过基本算法
So, how many people would like to see
那么 有多少人愿意看
why the standard algorithm is bad?
为什么基本算法不好
Because it's not totally obvious.
因为这真的不是很显然的事
One, two, three, four, five, half?
1 2 3 4 5 一半的同学
Wow, that's a lot of votes.
不错哦 很多人想看
Now, how many people want to skip to the chase?
有多少人想直接看重点
No one. One, OK. And, everyone else is asleep.
没有 哦 有一个 然后其他人都睡着了
So, that's pretty good, 50% awake, not bad.
看来还行啊 有一半人没被我催眠
OK, then, so standard matrix multiplication.
那么 我们先做基本矩阵乘法吧
I'll do this fast because it is, I mean,
我会做得很快的 因为嘛
you all know the algorithm, right?
你们都很熟悉它了 是吧
To compute this value of C;
要计算结果矩阵C
in A, you take this row, and in B you take this column.
在A矩阵里 你是取行 在B矩阵 你是取列
Sorry I did a little bit sloppily.
不好意思 我画得马虎了
But this is supposed to be aligned. Right?
但这两个向量应该是对齐的
So I take all of this stuff,
那么 我用这些东西
I multiply it with all of the stuff, add them up,
乘上这些东西 再加起来
the dot product. That gives me this element.
这就是点乘运算 得出这一个元素
And, let's say I do them in this order row by row.
然后 我们按照这个顺序一行一行乘下来
So for every item in C,
对于矩阵C中的每一个元素
I loop over this row and this column, B,
每步循环里 我都把这一行跟着一列
multiply them together. That is an access pattern in memory.
相乘起来 这就是它内存的读取模式
So, exactly how much that costs depends
那花费的多少是取决于
how these matrices are laid out in memory.
这个矩阵在内存里的分布形式
OK, this is a subtlety we haven't had to worry about before
这种事太琐碎了 我们之前都不会考虑的
because everything was uniform.
因为所有东西都是均匀的
I'm going to assume to give the standard algorithm
我假设我们的基本算法
the best chances of being good,
在它最好的情况下运作
I'm going to store C in row major order,
我要按行来存储矩阵C
A in row major order, and B in column major order.
矩阵A也是按行存储 而矩阵B则是按列存储
So, everything is nice and you're scanning.
所以 当你做扫描时 一切都是很顺手的
So then this inner product is a scan.
所以 每一个点乘运算都是一次扫描
Cool. Sounds great, doesn't it? It's bad, though.
酷炫啊 好像很厉害的样子 其实就是渣渣
Assume A is row major, and B is column major.
假设矩阵A按行存储 矩阵B按列存储
And C, you could assume is really either way,
而矩阵C 你想怎么都可以
but if I'm doing it row by row, I'll assume it's row major.
但如果我是一行一行地做 我就按行存储
So, this is what I call the layout,
这就是我说的存储分布
the memory layout, of these matrices.
这些矩阵在内存里的分布
OK, it's good for this algorithm,
这对于算法来说是不错的
but the algorithm is not good.
但这个算法本身太废了
So, it won't be that great.
所以 结果就不行了
So, how long does this take?
这需要花多长时间
How many memory transfers? We know it takes M^3 time.
又需要多少存储传输量 我们知道它要花M^3的时间
Not going to try and beat M^3 here. Just going to try to
我们不是要让时间突破M^3的界限
get standard matrix multiplication going faster.
我们只是想把基本矩阵乘法加快一点
So, well, for each item over here
所以呢 对于矩阵C的每一个元素
I pay N over B to do the scans and get the inner product.
我都要花费N/B来扫描并做点乘运算
So, N over B per item. So, it's N over B,
每个元素都要N/B 所以要计算C_ij
or we could go with the plus one here,
可能我这里也要写一个+1
to compute each c_ij. So that would suggest,
花费就是N/B 这就意味着
as an upper bound at least, it's N^3 over B.
它的上界至少是N^3/B
OK, and indeed that is the right bound, so theta.
实际上 这也是它的确界 也就是Θ符号
This is memory transfers, not time, obviously.
这个是存储传输量 很显然 这不是时间
That is indeed the case because if you look at consecutive,
这是真实的情况 因为如果你连续地做点乘
I do this c_ij, then this one, this one...
我先做这个C_ij 然后做这个 这个
keep incrementing j and keeping I fixed, right?
保持i不变 不断增大j 对吧
So, the row that I use stays fixed for a long time.
所以我在很长一段时间内 都停留在这一行
I get to reuse that if it happens,
如果它跟数据块大小吻合的话
say that that fits a block maybe,
我可以不断重用这一行的数据
I get to reuse that row several times
我可以重用这一行好几次
if that happens to fit in cache.
如果它跟缓存大小吻合
But the column is changing every single time.
但这些列就每次都在变化了
OK, so every time I moved here and compute the next c_ij,
所以 每次我移动一格 计算下一个C_ij时
even if a column could fit in cache,
就算一列跟缓存吻合
I can't fit all the columns in cache.
我也不能把所有列都放进缓存里
And the columns that I'm visiting move, you know,
而要访问的列就一直往这边移动
they just scan across.
我们要这样扫过去
So, I'm scanning this whole matrix every time.
我每次都要扫描一整个矩阵
And unless you're entire matrix fits in cache,
除非你能把整个矩阵装进缓存
in which case you could do anything, I don't care,
这样你就万能了 我什么都不用管
it will take constant time, or you'll take M over B time,
这就只需要常数时间就好 或者是M/B的时间
enough to read it into the cache,
够你把它读到缓存里
do your stuff, and write it back out.
干完你要干的事 把东西写回
Except in that boring case,
而在这种没意思的情况中
you're going to have to pay N^2 over B for every row here
你只需要做N^2/B次读取 来计算这里的每一行
because you have to scan the whole collection of columns.
因为你需要把所有的列都扫描一遍
You have to read this entire matrix for every row over here.
这里每做一行 就要扫描这里一整个矩阵
So, you really do need N^3 over B for the whole thing.
所以你整个做下来真的要花费N^3/B
So, it's usually a theta.
所以 这一般都用Θ符号
So, you might say, well, that's great.
你可能会说 很好很强大
It's the size of my problem,
这就是用我问题的大小
the usual running time, divided by B.
也就是一般的运行时间 除以B
And that was the case when we are thinking about linear time,
但这种想法只适用于线性时间的情况上
N versus N over B.
N对应N/B
It's hard to beat N over B when your problem is of size N.
如果问题大小为N 要比N/B更好确实很难
But now we have a cubed. And, this gets back to,
但现在我们的问题是N^3 这就回到了
we have good spatial locality.
数据的空间局部性问题
When we read a block, we use the whole thing.
当我读取一个数据块 我会就用到整一块
Great. It seems optimal.
不错 好像挺高效
But we don't have good temporal locality.
但我们没有良好的时间局部性
It could be that maybe if we stored the right things,
假设我们(在缓存里)存了合适的数据块
we kept them around, we could use them several times
我把它一直留着 然后可以不断重用
because we're using each element like a cubed number of times.
因为每一个元素我都要用N^3次
That's not the right way of saying it,
这样说好像不太对
but we're reusing the matrices a lot, reusing those items.
但我们还是会经常地重用这些元素
If we are doing N^3 work on N^2 things,
如果我们要在N^2的数据上做N^3的操作
we're reusing a lot. So, we want to do better than this,
那就要重用很多次了 所以 要做得比这个更好
and that's the recursive algorithm, which we've seen.
那就要用递归算法 我们也学过了
So, we know the algorithm pretty much.
我们应该对它很了解
I just have to tell you what the layout is.
我只需要说明它是如何分布的
So, we're going to take C,
那么 我们就把矩阵C
partition of C_1-1, C_1-2, and so on.
分割成C_1-1 C_1-2 如此类推
So, I have an N by N matrix,
原矩阵是N*N的
and I'm partitioning into N over 2 by N over 2 submatrices,
我现在把它分割为N/2 * N/2的子矩阵
all three of them
把矩阵A B C都分割开
times whatever.
然后乘上矩阵B
And, I could write this out yet again but I won't.
我就不把所有东西重画一遍了
OK, we can recursively compute this thing
我可以递归地计算
with eight matrix multiplies,
这里八个矩阵的相乘
and a bunch of matrix additions.
然后再做矩阵相加
I don't care how many, but a constant number.
我都不乎有多少个了 反正是常数个
We see that at least twice now, so I won't show it again.
因为我们至少做过2遍了 所以我就不画出来了
Now, how do I lay out the matrices?
那么 我要怎么安排这个矩阵的分布
Any suggestions how I lay out the matrices?
要不要再问问元芳怎么看
I could lay them out in row major order.
我可以把它们按行分布
I'll call it major order.
我就直接叫行分布得了
But that might be less natural now.
但现在事情好像不那么自然了
We're not doing anything by rows or by columns.
因为现在既不是按行 也不是按列运算
So, what layout should I use?
那我该用什么分布
Yeah? Quartet major order,
啥 四重分布
maybe quadrant major order unless you're musically inclined,
你想说四分分布吧 都快成四重奏了
Yeah. Good idea.
嗯 想法不错
You've never seen this order before,
你们其实见过这种分布
so it's maybe not so natural.
虽然好像不太自然
Somehow I want to cluster it by blocks.
我的确想设法把它们聚拢成块
OK, I think that's about all.
好的 我想就是这样了
So, I mean, it's a recursive layout.
我的意思是 它是一个递归的分布
This was not an easy question. It's OK.
这不是简简单单的事 但还凑合
Store matrices or lay out the matrices recursively by block.
递归地用数据块来存储一个矩阵
OK, I'm cheating a little bit.
我其实走的不是寻常路
I'm redefining the problem to say,
我把问题重新定义一下
assume that your matrices are laid out in this way.
假设你的矩阵是这样分布的
But, it doesn't really matter.
但其实也影响不大
We can cheat, can't we?
我们可以走点捷径 是吧
In fact, it doesn't matter.
真的 这不会有很大影响
You can turn a matrix into this layout
你可以把矩阵换成这种分布
without too much linear work,
只需要花费线性的工作量 不多
almost linear work. Log factors, maybe.
几乎是线性的功 可能还带log因子
OK, so if I want to store my matrix A as a linear thing,
如果我想把矩阵A存成线性的样子
I'm going to recursively defined that layout
我就可以递归地把分布定义为
to be recursively store the upper left corner,
递归地存储左上角
then store, let's say, the upper right corner.
然后是右上角
It doesn't matter which order I do these.
这个顺序无所谓的
I should have drawn this wider,
我把它画得宽一些
then store the lower left corner,
然后存左下角
and then store the lower right corner recursively.
然后再递归地存右下角
So, how do you store this? Well, you divide it in four,
那么 你要怎么存这一块 简单 你再分成四块
and lay out the top left, and so on.
然后再存左上角 如此类推
OK, this is a recursive definition of
这个就是如何递归地
how the element should be stored in a linear array.
把矩阵元素存在线性数组里
It's a weird one, but this is a very powerful idea
虽然有点奇怪 但却是非常给力的想法
in cache oblivious algorithms.
对于缓参无关算法来说
We'll use this multiple times.
我们会多次用到这个思想
OK, so now all we have to do
而现在 我们要做的
is analyze the number of memory transfers.
就是分析存储传输量
It seems...How hard could it be?
感觉嘛...好像好难啊
So, we're going to store all the matrices in this order,
所以 我们按照这种方式把矩阵存起来
and we want to compute the
然后 我们要计算
number of memory transfers on an N by N matrix.
N*N矩阵的存储传输量
See, I lapsed and I switched to lowercase n.
有没有看到 我这失手写成小写n了
I should, throughout this week,
但这一周里 我其实应该
be using uppercase N because for historical reasons,
都用大写N写 由于某些历史问题
any external memory kinds of algorithms,
所有的外部存储算法
two level algorithms, always talk about capital N.
比如两层算法 总是用到大写N
And, don't ask why.
有事就去问神奇海螺吧
You should see what they define little n to be.
你们应该看看他们对小写n都做了什么
So, any suggestions on what the recurrence should be now?
好的 现在你们对这个递归式有什么想法
All this fancy setup with the recurrence is actually pretty easy.
虽然这个递归式的设定好像很繁琐 但其实它并不难
So, definitely it involves multiplying matrices
首先 它肯定包含了
that are N over 2 by N over 2.
N/2 * N/2的矩阵乘法
So, what goes here?
那这里是多少
Eight, thank you.
是8 唔该晒
That you should know.
这个你们应该能想到
And that the tricky part is what goes here.
然而 接下来的步骤就有技巧性了
OK, what goes here is, now,
那这里是什么
the fact that I can even write this,
实际上 我只写这一个也没问题
this is the matrix additions.
后面的是矩阵加法
Ignore those for now. Suppose there weren't any.
现在可以无视它 当它不存在
I just have to recursively multiply.
我只需要考虑递归相乘
The fact that this actually is eight times
而这里 导致8乘以MT(N/2)的情况
memory transfers of N over 2 relies on this layout.
完全跟这一个矩阵分布有关
Right, I'm assuming that the arrays that I'm given
好了 我假设我给出的这个数组
are given as contiguous intervals and memory.
它在内存里是一段连续的空间
If they aren't, I mean,
如果不是的话
if they're scattered all over memory, I'm screwed.
如果它们是分散存放在内存里 我就GG了
There's nothing I can do.
难为巧妇啊
So, but by assuming that I have this recursive layout,
但如果我假设我有这样的递归分布
I know that the recursive multiplies will
我就知道 递归相乘总是会
always deal with three consecutive chunks of memory,
调用到三块连续的内存
one for A, one for B, one for C,
一块是矩阵A 一块是B 一块是C
OK, no matter what I do.
那无论我做什么都好
Because these are stored consecutively,
因为它们是连贯地存储在一起的
recursively I have that invariant.
递归下来也是如此
And I can keep recursing.
然后我就不断递归
And I'm always dealing with three consecutive chunks of memory.
而我总是会调用三块连续的内存
That's why I need this layout is to be able to say this.
我要这种分布的原因就是为了这样子
OK, Now what does addition cost?
那么 矩阵相加的花费是多少
I'll just give you two matrices.
我给你两个矩阵
They're stored in some linear order,
它们是线性存储的
the same linear order among the three of them.
这三个矩阵都是一样的线性存储
Do I care what the linear order is?
我要操心线性存储吗
How should I add two matrices, get the output?
我要怎么把两个矩阵相加 然后得到结果的
Yeah?
请说
Right, if each of the three arrays I'm dealing with
对了 如果我要调用的这三个数组
are stored in the same order,
都是用一样的存储形式
I can just scan in parallel through all three of them
我可以直接并行地扫描它们三个
and just add corresponding elements, and output it to the third
把两个数组相加 结果放到第三个数组里
So, I don't care what the order is,
那我就不用管具体什么形式了
as long as it's consistent and I get N^2 over B.
只要它们是一致的 我就能得到N^2/B
I'll ignore plus one here.
这里我就省略+1了
That's just looking at the entire matrix.
这是从整个矩阵来看的结果
So, there we go: another recurrence.
好吧 又有一条递归式
We've seen this with N^2, and we just got N^3.
我们才讲过 如果这是N^2 结果解出来就是N^3
But, it turns out now we get something
但现在 如果我们用对了基础条件
cooler if we use the right base case.
我们好像可以得到更加帅气的东西
So now we get to the base case, ah, the tricky part.
那就又轮到单位情况的回合了 啊 又有秘技了
So, any suggestions what base case I should use?
谁来说说这次我要用什么单位情况
The block size, good suggestion.
数据块大小 好想法
So, if we have something of size order B,
如果我们有个B阶大小的东西
we know that takes a constant number of memory transfers.
我们就知道它需要常数阶的存储传输量
It turns out that's not enough.
但其实这还不够
That won't solve it here.
还不能解决问题
But good guess. In this case, it's not the right answer.
但猜得有一手 虽然在这里不是正确答案
I'll give you some intuition why.
我给你们一些直观的解释吧
We are trying to improve on N^3 over B.
我们想对N^3/B做改进
If you were just trying to get it divided by B,
如果你只是想通过除以B来改进
this is a great base case.
这个单位情况就挺好
But here, we know that just the improvement
但在这 我们意识到
afforded by the block size is not enough.
仅仅通过块大小来改进还不够
We have to somehow use the fact that the cache is big.
我们要利用到缓存很大这个条件
It's M, so however big M is, it's that big.
缓存大小是M 不管M具体多少 反正是很大
OK, so if we want to get some improvement on this,
如果我们要对这个做改进
we've got to have M in the formula somewhere,
那这条式子里面要用到参数M
and there's no M's yet.
但这里还没有
So, it's got to involve M. What's that?
那我们就设法把它加进来 你说啥
MT of M over B? That would work, but MT of M is also OK,
MT(M/B) 我看行 其实MT(M)就好了
I mean, some constant times M, let's say.
应该说 常数c乘以M才对
I want to make this constant small enough
我想让这个常数足够小
so that the entire problem fits in cache.
这样整个问题都能放进缓存里了
So, it's like one third. I think it's actually,
所以 它大致是1/3 可能不是那么的准确
oh wait, is it the square root of M actually?
哦 等一下 好像应该是M的平方根
Right, this is an N by N matrix.
没错 这是N*N矩阵
So, it should be C times the square root of M. Sorry.
所以这应该是c乘以M的平方根 不好意思
So the square root of M by square root of M matrix has M entries
M的平方根乘以M的平方根就得到M个条目
If I make C like one third or something,
如果我把c设定成1/3神马的
then I can fit all three matrices in memory.
我就刚好能把三个矩阵都放进缓存里了
Actually, one over square root of three would do, but who cares?
其实根号3分之一就好了 但管他呢
So, for some constant C, now everything fits in memory.
所以 对于某个常数c而言 所有东西都能装进缓存
How many memory transfers does it take?
那这一共要多少存储传输量
One?
一个
It's a bit too small,
太小了吧
because I do have to read the problem in.
因为我要把整个问题都读进来
And now, I mean, here was one
现在的话 这是1
because there's only one block to read.
因为这只有一个数据块
Now how many blocks are there to read?
那这里要读多少个块
Constants? No.
常数个 不对
B? No. M over B, good.
B 错了 是M/B 终于说对了
Get it right eventually.
你们是乱猜的吗
That's the great thing about thinking with an oracle.
爆种不是这么爆的啊 骚年们
You can just keep guessing.
不要一直乱猜啊
M over B because we have cache size M.
M/B是因为我们缓存大小是M
There are M over B blocks in that cache to read each one, OK?
所以缓存里一共有M/B个块 如果把全部都读进来的话
This is maybe, you forgot what M was
这可能是因为你们已经忘掉M了
because we haven't used it for a long time.
因为我们没提到它很久了
But M is the number of elements in cache.
但M是缓存里的元素容量
This is the number of blocks in cache.
而M/B则是缓存里的块的数量
OK, someone was saying B,
有些人说是B
and it's reasonable to assume that M over B is about B.
如果要假设M/B就是B也是合理的
That's like a square cache,
那样缓存就是正方形的了
but in general, we don't make that assumption.
但一般我们不会这么假设
OK, where are we? We're hopefully done,
我们讲到哪了 希望已经讲完了
just about, good, because we have three minutes.
因为就快要...很好 我们还有三分钟
So, that's our base case. I have a square root here;
所以 这就是我们的单位情况 这是一个平方根
I just forgot it. Now we just have to solve it.
我刚刚忘记了 现在我们就来解它
Now, this is an easier recurrence, right?
那么 这个递归式还算简单吧
I don't want to use the master method,
我不想用主方法了
because master method is not going to handle these B's and M's,
因为主方法管不了这些参数B和M
and these crazy base cases.
还有这个暴走的单位情况
OK, master method would prove N^3. Great.
主方法会证明出N^3来 无敌了
Master method doesn't really think about these kinds of cases.
主方法不会考虑这些情况的
But with recursion trees, if you remember
但对于递归树来说 如果你还记得
way back to the proof of the master method,
主方法是怎么证明的
just look at the recursion tree
就是先看递归树
as geometric up or down or everything is equal,
它要不是几何递增递减 要不就是都相等
and then you just add them up, every level.
而你只需要把每层都加起来
The point is that this is a nice recurrence.
重点是 这是一个很漂亮的递归式
All of the sub problems are the same size,
所有的子问题大小都一样
and that analysis always works, I say,
而且这个分析一直都是成立的
when everything has the same size, all the children.
我是说 所有子节点大小都一样
So, here's the recursion tree.
那么 这就是递归树
We have N^2 over B at the top.
根部是N^2/B
We split into eight subproblems
我们把它分成8个子问题
where each one the cost is one half N^2 over B.
每一个都是N^2/B的一半
I'm not going to write them all. There they are.
我就不都写出来了 它们都是一样的
You add them up. How much do you get?
你把它们加起来 然后得到多少
Well, there's eight of them. Eight times a half is two, right?
嗯 一共有八个 8乘以1/2等于2 是吧
Four. [LAUGHTER] Thanks. Four, right? OK
额 4才对 谢谢 是4吧
I'm bad at arithmetic. I probably already said it,
我的数学老师死得早 让你们贱笑了
but there are three kinds of mathematicians,
世上只有三种数学家
those who can add, and those who can't.
一种会数数 另一种不会
OK, why am I looking at this? It's obvious.
我还看这个干啥 这显然如此
OK, so we keep going.
好的 我们继续
This looks geometrically increasing. Right?
这看起来像是几何递增 是吧
Four, OK? You just know in your heart
是4 没错吧 你要记住
that if you have a recurance, work out the first two levels,
如果你有一条递归式 先解出前两层
you can tell whether it's geometrically increasing, decreasing
然后你就能分辨它是几何递增 还是递减
or they're all equal,
还是都相等
or something else. And then you better think.
或者其他神马 但要你自己想
But I see this as geometrically increasing.
但我看这个应该是几何递增
It will indeed be like 16 at the next level, I guess.
它下一层应该会是16 我觉得
OK, it should be.
应该是这样
So, it's increasing, that means the leaves matter.
所以 它是递增的 这意味着叶节点也有用
So, let's work out the leaves.
那我们就来算算叶节点
And, this is where we use our base case.
而这也是我们用到单位条件的地方
So, we have a problem of size square root of M.
那么 我们的问题大小是根号M
And so, yeah, you have a question?
所以 你有什么高见
Oh, indeed. I knew there was something.
哦 确实 我就觉得有问题
I knew it was supposed to be two out here.
我知道这应该是2的
Thanks. This is why you're here.
非常感谢 这说明了你们来上课绝非打酱油
It's actually N over two over root B. Thanks.
这实际上是(N/2)^2/B 谢谢
I'm substituting N over 2 into this.
我把N/2替换了成这个
OK, so this is actually N^2 over 4 B.
所以这个实际上是N^2/4B
So, I get two, because there are eight times one over four.
所以 求出来得到是2 因为是8乘以1/4嘛
OK, I wasn't that far off then.
好吧 其实我没算错
It's still geometrically increasing, still the case, OK?
这依然还是几何递增的 还是这样吧
But now, it actually doesn't matter.
但现在 这已经不重要了
Whatever the cost is, as long as it's bigger than one, great.
无论花费是多少 只要是大于1的话 好的
Now we look at the leaves.
我们还是看叶节点吧
The leaves are root M by root M.
叶节点是根号M乘根号M
I substitute root M into this:
我把根号M替换成这个
I get M over B with some constants. Who cares?
我得到M/B和一些不重要的常数
So, each leaf is M over B,
每一个叶节点都是M/B
OK, lots of them. How many are there?
有很多叶节点 很多是多少
This is the only, deal with recursion trees,
这就只是解递归树了
counting the number of leaves is always the annoying part.
每次数叶节点数量都是很麻烦的
Oh boy, well, we start with an N by N matrix.
骚年啊 我们还是从N*N矩阵开始吧
We stop when we get down to root N by root N matrix.
一直到根号N乘根号N矩阵结束
So, that sounds like something.
这看起来像是...
Oh boy, I'm cheating here. Really? That many?
我要看看作弊小抄 真的 有这么多
It sounds plausible. OK, the claim is, and I'll cheat.
好像还是有理的 好吧 我出千了
So I'm going to use the oracle here,
我要用外挂直接出答案
and we'll figure out why this is the case.
然后再讨论为什么是这个
N over root N^3 leaves,
N除以N^3的平方根
hey what? I think here, it's hard to see the tree.
不勒个是吧 虽然在树里很难看出来
But it's easy to see in the matrix.
但在矩阵里就比较容易了
Let's enter the matrix.
来进入黑客帝国吧
We have our big matrix. We divided in half.
我们有一个大矩阵 我们把它对半分
We recursively divide in half.
不断递归地对半分
You get the idea, OK?
你懂的
Now, at some point these sectors,
好了 到了某个地步 这些分段..
let's say one of these sectors, and each of these sectors,
或者说某一个分段 每一个分段
fits in cache. And three of them fit in cache.
与缓存大小吻合 三小段恰好填满缓存
So, that's when we stop the recursion in the analysis.
这就是我们停止递归分析的地方
The algorithm goes all the way.
这个算法会不断跑下去
But in the analysis, let's say we stop at M.
但在分析里 我们会在M停止
OK, now, how many leaves of problems are there?
那么 现在我有多少个叶节点
Oh man, this is still not obvious.
坑爹啊 这还是不怎么明显
OK, the number of leaf chunks here is, like, I mean,
好吧 这些小方块的数量是
the number of these things is something like N over root M,
大概是N除以根号M吧
right, the number of chunks.
对了 是小方块的数量
But, it's a little less clear because I have so many of these.
但这样说好像不太清楚 因为这里有很多个小方块
But, all right, so let's just suppose,
但好吧 我们不如假设
now, I think of normal, boring, matrix multiplication
我们考虑的 是普通又无趣的矩阵乘法
on chunks of this size.
它就是用这种大小的方块
That's essentially what the leaves should tell me.
而这个大小是通过叶节点求得的
I start with this big problem,
我从这个大问题开始
I recurse down to all these little, tiny, multiply this by that
递归地把问题缩小 拿这个(小块)乘以那个
OK, this root M by root M chunk.
就是这个根号M * 根号M的小块
OK, how many operations,
那要做多少运算
how many multiplies do I do on those things? N^3.
我要做多少次乘法 N^3
But now, N, the size of my matrix
但对应整个矩阵而言 大小才为N
in terms of these little sub matrices, is N over root M.
而对于这些子矩阵来说 大小就是N/M
So, it should be N over root M^3 subproblems of this size.
所以 子问题的大小应该是O((N/M)^3)
If you work it out,
如果你继续向下算
normally we go down to things of constant size
一般我们会递减到常数级的大小
and we get exactly N^3 of them.
然后我们恰好有N^3个子问题
Now we are stopping at this short point in saying,
那现在 我们做到这一步就停止了
well, it's however many there are, cubed.
这有多少个叶节点 N^3个
OK, this is a bit of hand waving.
好的 你们可以欢呼雀跃了
You could work it out with the recurrence
其实不用解递归式 你也可以
on the number of leaves. But there it is.
求出叶节点数 就是这样
So, the total here is N over, let's work it out.
所以 总数就是N除以...我们算一下吧
N^3 over M to the three halves, that's this number of leaves,
是N^3除以M^(3/2) 这是叶子的数量
times the cost at each leaf, which is M over B.
再乘以每一个叶子的花费 也就是M/B
So, some of the M's canceled, and we get N^3 over B root M,
有些M被消掉了 然后我们得到N^3 / (B * M^0.5)
which is a root M factor better than N^3 over B.
这跟N^3/B相比少了一个根号M的因子
It's actually quite a lot, the square root of the cache size.
这其实已经很多了 是缓存大小的平方根这么多
That is optimal.
是一个最优解了
The best two level matrix multiplication algorithm
最好的两层模型矩阵相乘算法
is N^3 over B root M memory transfers.
就是要N^3 / (B * M^0.5)这么多的存储传输量
Pretty amazing, and I'm over time.
简直是个奇迹 然后我又拖堂了
You can generalize this into all sorts of great things,
你们可以把这些都演化成各种强大的东西
but the bottom line is this is a great way
但至少可以肯定的一点是
to do matrix multiplication as a recursion.
用递归来做矩阵乘法实在是太棒了
We'll see more recursion for cache oblivious algorithm
我们之后再继续讨论缓参无关算法
on Wednesday.
周三见